Pierre Bourdelle Papers
Pierre Bourdelle Papers
1938-1966
Bourdelle, Pierre
34 linear ft.
Personal papers including correspondence, 1948-1966; financial records; an address book, and a weekly time book, 1938. Artwork includes anatomical sketches, negatives, file photographs, and other sketches, both original and published.
148860
Biographical History
Pierre Bourdelle ( 1903-1966) was a sculptor, painter, and muralist. He was born in 1903 in Paris. He was the son of Emile Antoine Bourdelle and Stephanie Van Parys Bourdelle, two French artists. Emile Bourdelle was the assistant of August Rodin, the famous French sculptor. Pierre was educated in his father's studio through an apprenticeship. Upon his father's death he immigrated to the United States where he became an artist in his own right. During what were to become the last years of his life, he taught at C.W. Post, which is part of the Long Island University, as an artist-in-residence. He died in 1966.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Pierre Bourdelle Papers consist of five parts: Artwork, Published Material, Subject Files, Writings, and Oversized Packages. Artwork includes actual paintings and sketches, as well as a comprehensive series of photgraphs of completed work. Published Material contains clippings of all sorts of subjects such as animals, science, people, and of course, art. Subject Files covers a wide range of material including correspondence with the American Battle Monuments Commission about Bourdelle's work for them on a war monument at St. Avold France. It also includes correspondence from between the years 1955-1966, and Bourdelle's fianancial records from his years in Haiti. Writings contains many of Bourdelle's notes as an art history teacher at C.W. Post. Oversized Packages include portfolios containing photographs of artwork, scrapbooks, paintings, prints, sketches, watercolors, murals, and posters.
Arrangement of the Collection
Boxes 1-5 contain Bourdelle's Artwork, which has been divided loosely into sketches, photographs and negatives. The subject matter is listed alphabetically where applicable. Published Material can be found in box 6 and consists of various clippings. It is followed by the Subject Files (boxes 6-7) which are listed in alphabetical order. These contain a myriad of items such as address books, materials pertaining to Post College, correspondence, financial accounts and ledgers, and other writings. The Pierre Bourdelle Papers also include 43 Oversized Packages, which contain photographs, scrapbooks, prints, sketches, watercolors, posters, murals, and paintings, in no particular order.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Art -- Sculptors; Bourdelle, Pierre.; Artists -- United States.; Art, Modern -- 20th century.; Mural painting and decoration -- United States -- 20th century.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, Modern -- 20th century.; Address books.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Notes (documents); Photonegatives.; Photographs.; Sketches.; Artists.; Painters.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ruth Bourdelle, 1969.
Inventory
- Artwork
  - Anatomical sketches - forearm, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Birth announcement, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Canadian pacific railroad
    - #154 A Industries, paper, oil, textiles, steel, et.; 1 folder (Box 1)
    - #154 B Nature, flowers, leaves, wildlife; 1 folder (Box 1)
    - #154 C Out of doors work, formaing, fishing, lumbering; 1 folder (Box 1)
    - #154 D Sports, skiing, fishing, riding; 1 folder (Box 1)
    - #154 E Boating, fishing, sailing, ship building; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Negatives
    - Booklet and slides, 4 folders, 2 in each box (Box 1, 2)
    - Color slide sheets, 6 folders, 3 in each box (Box 1, 2)
    - Color transparencies, 2 folders, 1 in each box (Box 1, 2)
    - Black and white strips, 2 small boxes, 1 in each main box (Box 1, 2)
    - Color singles, 2 small boxes, 1 in each main box (Box 1, 2)
  - Photographs, See also Subject Files in Box 6 and Oversized Packages for more photographs.
    - Bas-relief, sculpture, N.S. Savannah (Box 2)
    - Assorted metal works (Box 2)
    - Sculpture and metal sculpture photos (Box 3)
    - Cement and wood abstracts (Box 3)
    - Face sculptures (Box 3)
    - Photos of drawings (Box 3)
    - Photos of drawings, abstracts and cultures (Box 3)
    - File prints (Box 4)
    - 5 albums (Box 4)
    - General, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Harlequin, metal and glass (Box 5)
    - Kohlev Auditorium; metal (Box 5)
    - Latest prints (Box 5)
    - Lykes cabins (Box 5)
    - Lykes lounge panel (Box 5)
    - Nature (Box 5)
    - Plexiglass works (Box 5)
    - St. Dominic, lacquer relief (Box 5)
    - Sciences; metal (Box 5)
    - Sculpture portraits (Box 5)
    - Steph's head; sculpture (Box 5)
    - Stone sculpture (Box 5)
    - Sculptured heads (Box 5)
    - Sundial; metal (Box 5)
    - Railroad car decoration (Box 5)
    - Taurus - wine - centaur (Box 5)
    - Tiger mosaic; head (Box 5)
    - Working associates (Box 5)
  - Sketches, See also Oversized Packages for more sketches. (Box 5)
- Published Material
  - Clippings #1 (Box 6)
  - Clippings #2 (Box 6)
  - Clippings #3 (Box 6)
  - Clippings (Box 6)
  - Magazines (Box 6)
- Subject Files
  - Assorted unidentified photographs (Box 6)
  - Address books, 2 (Box 6)
  - Art course (Box 6)
  - Cadwalader, Wickersham and Taft (Box 6)
  - Caracas (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, general
    - 1955 (Box 6)
    - 1948-1954 (Box 6)
    - 1956-1957 (Box 6)
    - 1958-1966 (Box 6)
    - Undated (Box 6)
    - Heaney (Box 6)
  - Crystallography (Box 6)
  - C. W. Post College (Box 6)
  - Dana, 1962 (Box 7)
  - Financial (Box 7)
  - First National Bank, Dallas (Box 7)
  - Index cards (card file) of works (Box 7)
  - Ledgers (expenses), 1946; 1950 (Box 7)
  - L'Oiseau qui n'existe pas, 1965 (Box 7)
  - Mercantile bank (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Notebook "Where things are in house" (Box 7)
  - Notebook contents (Box 7)
  - St. Arold Monument, map for military cemetery (Box 7)
  - St. Dominic's Priory (Box 7)
  - Standard Bank of South Africa, Ltd., 1964 (Box 7)
  - Stock reports, 1949-1951 (Box 7)
  - Student writings (Box 7)
  - Travelogue, only partial Haiti expenses inside (Box 7)
  - Weekly time book, 1938 (Box 7)
- Writings
  - Art-related, 2 folders (Box 7)
- Oversized Packages
  - Scrapbooks, photographs, clippings, and articles (Oversize 1, 2)
  - Boxes of photographs, artwork (Oversize 3-7)
  - Portolio case, photographs of artwork (Oversize 8-10)
  - Scrapbooks, photographs of artwork (Oversize 11A, 11B, 12)
  - Prints, sketches and watercolors, Canada crests, figure studies, wildlife (Oversize 13)
  - Mural panels, prints and watercolors, technology, Greek myths (?) (Oversize 14)
  - Prints, watercolors, technology, Greek myths, birds (Oversize 15)
  - Prints in portfolios, prints, watercolors loose, technology, WW II map, myths (Oversize 16)
  - Murals, sketches, technology, laborers, "Sky Room" (Oversize 17)
  - Prints, sketches (Oversize 18)
  - Small paintings and pastels, "Pan American Petroleum and Transport Co., Inc. 1953 Annual Report," "Decibel Ceiling Tile Co. Catalog," paperboard animal sketches (Oversize 19)
  - Blueprints, paintings, posters, WW II maps, "Great Lakes," "St. John, St. Peter," "Prometheus and Electricity," "Riggers and Builders," "The Great Lakes," "Copper," "Chapel Blueprint" (Oversize 20)
  - Paintings, prints and sketches, "War," "Project for map 1/5," Bullfight (?), Laborers (?) (Oversize 21)
  - Small paintings, "Dogwood," "Chipmunk," "Coyote," "Cornstalk," "Cotton Bloom and Bole," "Antlered Buck" (Oversize 22)
  - Seashells and other prints (Oversize 23)
  - Prints, "Artillery," "Cavalry," Zodiac (?) (Oversize 24)
  - Watercolors, Ink Sketches, Landscapes, Abstract, Collage (Oversize 25)
  - Paintings, watercolors, cityscape, seascape, crucifix, figures, "Dieu," "The Miraculous Fishing," "The Miracle of Wine Jugs" (Oversize 26)
  - Pencil sketches, figures, blueprint sketch of airport (?), abstracts, women figures (?), Jesus (?) (Oversize 27)
  - Paintings, pencil sketches, wood puzzle figure, God Loves Texas (?), "Midsummer Night's Dream," "Sirens Creating the Motion of Waters that Determined the Consutruction of the Corresponding Seashells" (Oversize 28)
  - Murals, Paintings, "Braques Bird (?)," "Fiestas (?)," "Progress of the Worker" (Oversize 29)
  - Mural panel, Zodiac (?), Portfolio of 51 designs on canvas (Oversize 30)
  - 2 panel painting, published collection of Prints on WW II, Firing Squad (?), "Folio no. 143 of 250"; Removed for separate cataloguing, 4/2004 (Oversize 31)
  - 6 panel mural, Civilization (?) (Oversize 32)
  - Illustrations for O. Wilde, "The Sphinx" (Oversize 33)
  - Painting, Cowboy (?), Negative slide of painting of cowboy (Oversize 34)
  - Metal mural, Ship (Oversize 35)
  - 2 paper and ink sketches, rolls (Oversize 36)
  - 2 canvas paintings, rolls (Oversize 37)
  - 3 paper paintings, rolls (Oversize 38)
  - Boxes of photographs, artwork (Oversize 39-41)
  - Scrapbooks of photographs, artwork (Oversize 42)
  - Photographs of artwork (Oversize 43, 44)